<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dialogue or Familiar talke betwene two neighbours co[n]cernyng the chyefest ceremonyes, that were, by the mighti power of Gods most holie pure worde, suppressed in Englande, and nowe for vnworthines, set vp agayne by the bishoppes, the impes of Antichrist: right learned, profitable, and pleasaunt to be read, for the comfort of weake co[n]sciences in these troublous daies. Read first, and then iudge.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1554</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00273</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10383</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115543</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850762</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850762</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15988</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00273)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15988)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 566:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dialogue or Familiar talke betwene two neighbours co[n]cernyng the chyefest ceremonyes, that were, by the mighti power of Gods most holie pure worde, suppressed in Englande, and nowe for vnworthines, set vp agayne by the bishoppes, the impes of Antichrist: right learned, profitable, and pleasaunt to be read, for the comfort of weake co[n]sciences in these troublous daies. Read first, and then iudge.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[78] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Michael Wodde [i.e. John Day],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>From Roane [i.e. London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>the .xx. of February. Anno. Domi, M.D.L.IIII. [1554]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by STC to J. Bale.</note>
                  <note>The imprint is false. Suggested actual place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>With a catechism at the end.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E (-E8, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15988:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15988:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DIA<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>LOGVE OR FAMILIAR talke betwene two neighbours, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng the chyefeſt ceremonyes, that were, by the mighti power of Gods moſt holie pure worde, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in Englande, and nowe for our vnworthines, ſet vp agayne by the Biſhoppes, the impes of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt: right learned, profitable, and pleaſaunt to be read, for the comfort of weake co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences in theſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blous daies.</p>
            <p>Read firſt, and then iudge.</p>
            <p>From Roane, by Michael Wodde, the .xx. of February. Anno. Domi. M.D.L.IIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:15988:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15988:2"/>
            <head>A TALKE BETWENE OLY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a profeſſour of the Goſpell, and Nicholas noſeled in the blynde ſuperſtitions.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NIcholas.</speaker>
               <p>Good morow goſſyb.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>God gyue you good morow good Nicholas. why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther away ſo ſone this morning?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>To church man, heardeſt thou not the bell ryng to maſſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>Ye were not wont to be ſo haſty a morninges to church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>No, for when we came ther, ther was nothing to do but to heare a prieſt babble. But now I thancke God, I may ſe my maker againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Your maker Nicholas? who is that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>The great apple maker of holder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Apple maker? ye mean God, do you not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicholas.</speaker>
               <p>Yes marye do I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Olyu:</speaker>
               <p>Then I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that ſo long as Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes were read in the Churches, ye counted it bablyng, neither delited ye in hearing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but now ye haue ſomwhat to gaſe at, that pleaſeth ye. But Nicholas
<pb facs="tcp:15988:3"/> I haue heard it ſaid, that no man euer ſaw God wyth his mortall eye.<note place="margin">Ex. xxxiii. Iohn. i.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, theſe heritickes tell vs ſo, but I truſt to ſee a good mani of them fry a faggot for this geare, yet long.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Are ye there now Nicholas? I had went ye had loued and fauoured the word of God, ſet out by our late moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſe, vertuouſe, &amp; innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t king.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>So I dyd, as long as he ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but now that he is dead, I wil do as moſt men do, &amp; ſo ſhal few<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt men wonder at me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>In veri dede it is a politique worldli ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but Nicholas, thynckeſt thou that god is dead?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>Nay by my fayth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>what and God won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at the, to ſe the ſo vnconſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and vnſtedfaſt, waueryng as the wynde, as a weathereocke doth, that ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſteple?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Ther are no weathercockes then one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>Yea Nicholas that I thincke, and mo then ſtand vpon ſteeples alſo: but we ſhuld not do as the moſt do, but as the beſt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>So do I, for I do as the richeſt in al the country doth, and as all the greateſt learned men do,
<pb facs="tcp:15988:3"/> in al the countrey.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Rytches are a good gyft of God, but when they preuaile, and to much addict a mans hart vnto them, they make the ſame ſkant a good man. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are the greateſt clearkes the wiſeſt men alwai, nor yet the beſt. But they be the beſt, that prefer gods honour before all thynges, and that conſtantly abyde in the truth therof, how ſoeuer the ryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt men, &amp; greateſt clerkes turne them ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it. And this I mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel with what faces men can looke to be accompted Chriſtians, that deale ſo vnfaithfully with Chriſt. For eyther they tooke it for the truth, that was ſet out amongſt vs, or for an vntruth. Yf they tooke it for a truth, why do they now vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truly go from it, as though there wer no truth in it? Yf thei knew it to be no truth, but falſe doctrine, why dyd they not as Chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, defend that doctrine, which they knewe to be a truthe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>They durſt not for fear.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>wo worth that feare, that putteth away the feare of God, notwythſtandyng
<pb facs="tcp:15988:4"/> ther was no ſuche cauſe of feare. For al the raigne of that moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious king, their raigned mercye &amp; pitye, long ſufferaunce, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent abyding for amendes, euen of them, that when thei were confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſo that neither their wit, nor learning was able to withſtand the truth: yet maliciouſly they would not conſent nor agree vnto it, but outwardlye afore men, to flatter thoſe that were in authoritie, thei bare them ſelues as great forwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the kinges procedinges, as could be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and what they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, now appereth vnto al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>They were worldly wyſe men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Ye ſay truth. worldly wyſe in dede: but ſuch wiſdome is great foly before God, and vnto ſuch wiſe men (as Chriſt ſaith) ar the ſecretes of god hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo that thei neither haue faith in god, nor in his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue the feare of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, nor loue of his mercy: For theſe things ar geuen vnto babes, to the outcaſtes of this world, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ar cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted foles &amp; outcaſtes, as their
<pb facs="tcp:15988:4"/> maſter Chriſt was. Theſe do not ſeke to flatter kinges and prynces, but they ſeke to pleaſe God, and to ſet forth his truth, with the los (if God ſo lay the burthen vpon them) of goodes, frendes, name, &amp; eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their life. which of theſe trow ye, ar moſt worthy to be folowed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>I can not tel I. we dyd wel inough afore, and better then we haue done ſince, for we had neuer good world, ſince this geare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan. But our ſir Iohn telleth vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother leſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>what I prai the?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Mary that he maketh God euery day, at his maſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>Can ſyr Iohn make thy maker?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Yea that he doth euery dai.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>And doth he ſhew him vnto the?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, he is as faire a lifter, as ani is within Hamſhire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>And what doth he with hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afterward?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>what man? eat him, or hang him in the Pix.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Than he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him, and eateth him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>what els.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>what hangeth in the Pix?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Gods bodi ſacred.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſaydeſt ſyr Iohn dyd eate gods bodye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, ſo I
<pb facs="tcp:15988:5"/> ſaid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>How can he eate hym, &amp; hang him vp to?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>I can not reaſon ſuch hie matters. I beleue as our ſir Iohn telleth vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>who made goddes bodye ſacred?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Marye ſit Iohn.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>And who made ſir Iohn?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>God made him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>Then he is euen with god, and maketh him again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>we trow ſo, for ſir Ihon is a preſt anointed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>who made him a prieſt anoynted?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>The Biſhop.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>wherwyth anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted he him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>with oyle in the Chriſmatorye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>who made the Byſhoppe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>The Pope,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>Then the Pope made the Byſhop, the Byſhop greaſed ſyr Iohn. &amp; ſir Iohn made God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich</speaker>
               <p>By our bleſſed Ladye Oliuer, ye are as bad as the beſt, and I am ſory to ſe you fal to this new lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>In good faith Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las I am ſory to ſe you and many a thouſand mo, thus to fal againe from gods word, to your old ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious errours and idolatries,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>we beleue as our forefathers did.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>what cal ye forfathers?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:15988:5"/>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Mary my father, my grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and my great grandſire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Is thy father aliue?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, but he is at the laſt caſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>Howe long is it, ſince thy graundſire dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>He died .xx, yere ſynce, when I was twelue yere old.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>How thinkeſt thou, was not ſaint Peter and ſaint Paule forefathers?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Yes marye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>was not Chriſt a forefather?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>yes bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed mot he be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Nicholas, ye bleſſe Chriſt, but you cal his word, new learning, heriſie and babling.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Naye that I do not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>Did not you cal the holy readyng of the Byble ſo euen now?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>why? our ſir Iohn telleth vs it was made by king Harry theight.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>No good Nicholas no. That gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious king ſet it out, and commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the people ſhould reade it. without ani letting. But the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is gods boke, and al that is in it, is gods truth. Therfore the old fathers, that we ſhould folow, ar Chriſtes prophetes, and Apoſtles, and Chriſt him ſelfe, and not our old grandſires &amp; grandames. For
<pb facs="tcp:15988:6"/> God geueth an expreſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement,<note place="margin">zacha. i.</note> ſaying: Be not lyke your forefathers, vnto whom the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets cryed before tyme, ſaying: Thus ſaith the lord god of hoſtes. Turne from your euell waies, and from your wicked imaginations, &amp; they heared not, nor toke heede vnto me, ſaieth the Lorde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Our forefathers were good men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Olyuer.</speaker>
               <p>But yet Chriſt was better.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>They were wiſe men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, but yet Chriſte was wyſer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>They were holy men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>But Chriſt is holier. And what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer you can recken of them, good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes,<note place="margin">i. corin. i.</note> wiſedome, holynes. &amp;c. Chriſt excelleth them in al things. For he is made of god vnto vs, our wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, rightuouſnes, holines, ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Iho. xiiii.</note> and redemption. Chriſt is the way, the truth, and the life, and no man can come to the father, but by him. He that heareth. Chriſtes wordes, hath life euerlaſting. But Nicholas, tell me, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſir Iohn make an oxe, or an horſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Nay by mi truth. I trow not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>How can he the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make gods body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>It is
<pb facs="tcp:15988:6"/> no matter how, we muſt beleue ſo, for he ſaith ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Olyu.</speaker>
               <p>Nay Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, we muſt not beleue al that ſir Iohn ſaith, but we muſt beleue all that he ſaith, and hath gods word to confirme his ſaying. And this is an intollerable pride of the papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, to teach the people, that thei make gods body. Truth it is,<note place="margin">Eph. iiii.</note> that Chriſt aſcending into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, gaue gyftes vnto men, and appoynted church miniſters, but far other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> greaſed ſhauelinges: for he apoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted Apoſtles, prophetes, Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtes, Shepheardes and teachers.<note place="margin">Phili. i.</note> And ſaint Paule calleth the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the church, by the names of Biſhops and Deacons.<note place="margin">i. Tim. iii.</note> The of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of theſe miniſters appointed by Chriſt, and S. Paul,<note place="margin">Luk. xiiii</note> is to preach gods word, to cal al men to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce and amendement of life:<note place="margin">Iohn. xxi i. Tim. iiii</note> &amp; to declare to them that repent, the good newes of the goſpel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, the preſts wer wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to come to our houſes, &amp; to ſay vs goſpels, &amp; make vs holi water, &amp; holy bread: and ſo I truſt they wil again now.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>I pray the heare me a litle.
<pb facs="tcp:15988:7"/> The goſpel is a glad tidings that god the father,<note place="margin">Luke. ii.</note> for his ſonne Ieſus Chriſtes ſake,<note place="margin">ii. cori. v.</note> is contented, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, and receiueth ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againe to his fauour and grace,<note place="margin">Gala. iiii.</note> and wyll for his ſonne Ieſus Chriſtes loue, take vs (by adoptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) to be his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,<note place="margin">Epheſi. i.</note> giue vs his holy goſt, &amp; make vs enheritours of eternal life.<note place="margin">Ioh. xvii.</note> And to confirme this promiſe, our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſt hath ordained .ii. holy ſacraments:<note place="margin">Titus. iii.</note> Baptiſme, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are certified, that al our ſins are waſhed away, in the death of Chriſt:<note place="margin">i. corin. xi</note> And the holi ſupper of the lord, that when we come together we ſhould take the bread,<note place="margin">Mat, xxvi</note> breake it.<note place="margin">Mar. xiiii</note> &amp; eate it, in remembraunce that Chriſtes bodi was (vpon the good Fridai) offered vp, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe, for our ſinnes,<note place="margin">Luk. xxii,</note> and we ſhoulde al drinke of the cup, in re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>membrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that Chriſtes bloud was ſhed for our ſins. Therfore this is the prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes office, to preach the death of Ieſus Chriſt, and to teach the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple to know, that none other thing could deliuer them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſins, and therfore they ought both to
<pb facs="tcp:15988:7"/> conſyder the haynous vglines of ſin, and the great wrath of god o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it, which otherwiſe wold not be reconciled, nor atone with ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Rom. viii</note> Then on the other parte, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the great mercy, loue &amp; cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of god towards vs, that ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not his own beloued ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, but gaue him to the death of the cros for vs. Thus ſhoulde they be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to repent the euel done, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue and loue the charitie of God, &amp; to walke in loue, &amp; good frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, one to an other: euer ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to liue an obedient life, after the heauenly fathers wil and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Dothe not the prieſt make Gods bodye? Do we not eate gods body?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt anſwer me (if thou can) to a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion or two.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>I wil if I can.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>Canſt thou ſay thy Creede in Engliſhe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Meaneſt thou the new Creede, or the old Crede?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>There is but one Creede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>I can ſaye that my mother taught me, Credum deum. I was harping at the new a good while, but nowe I care not for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>I
<pb facs="tcp:15988:8"/> ſe it was not for nought that chriſt ſaid to his Apoſtles: bleſſed ar the eyes that ſe that you ſe,<note place="margin">Luke. x.</note> For euen as then mani were blind, and wold not ſe the light of his worde,<note place="margin">Iohn. ix.</note> euen ſo is it now, wel, I wil help you out with your queſtion. Do you not be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue, that the ſonne of God came downe from heauen, &amp; was borne for vs of the virgine Mary, takyng our mans nature of her ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Yes that I do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>And that he was crucified for our ſins, dead and buried, and roſe agayne vpon Eſterday?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Yes verely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>And that he aſcended into heauen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſitteth on the righte hand of God the father almighti?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Ye mary ye</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Olyu</speaker>
               <p>And fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence he ſhall come to iudge the quicke and the dead?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Ye ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Olyu.</speaker>
               <p>Do you beleue this in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dede?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Ye by my trothe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>Then Chriſtes bodye was made in the wombe of the virgin, not by ſir Iohn, but as our Creede ſaith, he was conceaued of the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly goſt,<note place="margin">Luke. i.</note> &amp; borne of the virgin mari. Other making of Chriſtes body, ther
<pb facs="tcp:15988:8"/> is none, nor neuer was, nor neuer ſhalbe. Thus our lord &amp; ſauiour li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued in this world,<note place="margin">Auguſt in Ioa. tract. Item in pref. pi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xcviii.</note> &amp; taught vs the wai of gods truth, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the doctrine that is ſet out in the holy Byble, wherof the chief and principal ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle is, how we are redemed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſinnes, and receaued into the fauour and grace of God, by that holy raunſome of Chriſtes bodye broken vpon the croſſe, &amp; his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blud that was on the croſſe ſhed for vs. The holy bread geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the lordes ſupper, is the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſtes bodye that was broken on the croſſe, and the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed cup that we drincke, is the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of that bleſſed blud ſhed for our ſynnes. And when we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them, as our body fedeth vp on the outwarde thinges we ſe, ſo our ſoules are fed with the inward thinges we ſee not. For the verye fleſh of Chriſt is not eaten wyth our bodilye tethe, nor his bloude dronke with our bodily mouthes or throtes: but it is a ſacramental eating, done bi the ſoule &amp; minde, not by the bodye or carnal inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:15988:9"/> of the body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Howe can we eate, but with our tethe, or how can we drincke but wyth our throtes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>You ſhal the better vnderſtande thys miſterye, if you marke Chriſtes dede, when his ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye ſacrament was firſt inſtituted. Chriſt him ſelfe ſatte at the table with his .xii. Apoſtles, and taking the bread, that ſtode before them, euen ſuch bread, as they then vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allye had to eate with the paſcall lambe, and gaue thanckes to hys heauenlye father, and brake that bread, and gaue it to them ſaying: Take, eate ye, this is mi bodi whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is broken for you. They dyd take the bread, and did eate as he commaunded them, and they dyd drincke the cup that he delyuered them ſaying: this is my bloude of the new teſtament, which is ſhed for you. Yet, it was the next daye, ere his bodye was broken, and hys bloud ſhed vpon the croſſe for vs, and he ſat whole amongſt them at ſupper, and him ſelfe did eate of that ſame bread, which he called his body, and dyd him ſelfe drink
<pb facs="tcp:15988:9"/> of that cuppe which he called his bloud, therfore by faith they dyd receyue and eate his body &amp; drink his bloud. They beleued that hys death and paſſion ſhoulde be for them, and into remiſſion for theyr ſinnes: as we now, that Chriſt is aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cended into heauen, by faith doo eate his body broken, and drincke his bloud ſhed, although that he liueth &amp; ſitteth on the right hand of his father. But Chriſtes veri na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall bodye is not toren with our teethe, as the Capernites erroure thincketh, nor yet his bloud dornk with our throtes &amp; mouthes. But Nicholas, haue you not a ſoule as wel as a bodye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Yes that I haue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>what maner of thing is your ſoule?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>By mi troth I can not tel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Olyu.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las no more ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the greateſt doctor of them al. And therfore becauſe the ſoule is vnknowen vnto vs, the ſcripture ſpeaking of the ſoule &amp; thoſe thinges that appertain vnto it, vſeth ſuch wordes as we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with, &amp; aſcribeth thoſe things vnto the ſoule that ar pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb facs="tcp:15988:10"/> vnto the body. So Dauid ſaid: My ſoule O Lorde thirſteth vnto the. And Chriſt ſaith: Bleſſed are thoſe that hunger and thurſte for rightuouſnes. The harty deſire of the ſoule, is the hunger and thurſt of the ſoule: as the herty deſire of meate and drincke is the hunger &amp; thurſt of the bodi. Therfore when a ſinner feleth the burden of ſinne vpon his conſcience, and the lacke of ſtrength and power, to do the wyl of God, and is touched wyth gods ſpirit, to be ſory for this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectnes, and longeth fain to be deliuered, this is the hunger of the ſoule. This hunger is not ſatiſfied tyl he heare the preaching of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes bodie broken for our ſinnes, &amp; that by his bloudſhed, our ſynnes ar forgiuen vs, our infirmities hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, &amp; we receiued into the grace and fauour of God. But when we beleue this, then is our hunger ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and our thurſt put away, that is: we feare no more dampnation, but knowe that in Chriſt we haue our pardon. Thus we eate Chriſt, beleuing that his body was broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15988:10"/> for vs, and that his blud was ſhed for our ſinnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>wherfore eat we the Sacrament than? we maye do this by hearing the preaching.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>I am glad <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  </hi> thou aſkeſt me this queſtion: for it ſeemeth thou wouldeſt faine vnderſtand ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this matter. As to writin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges men ſet to ſeales, for a confyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the ſame writinges, ſo Chriſt ſet to his worde, his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, for a confirmation of our faith, in his worde. And to put vs the better in memory of the gifte geuen vnto vs by his word, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſame Sacramentes, by the name of the gift geuen vnto vs in them. So circumciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is called the Lordes league, the paſcal lambe is called the Lordes paſſing thorow Egipt, Babtiſme is called the new birth, and the breade and wine is called the bodie and bloud of the Lord. Therefore Nicholas marke wel this. In the Lords Sacraments ther ar .ii. things, an earthli thing, and an heauenli. In Baptiſme, the earthli thing is water, that waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the bodie: the heauenlie thing
<pb facs="tcp:15988:11"/> is the blod of Chriſt, that waſheth the ſoule, and the holie goſt renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the hole man, and ſanctifying him in Ieſu Chriſt. In the holi ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per of the Lord, the earthli thing is bread and wine, that we receiue at our mouthes into our bodyes, which are digeſted in our ſtomaks, and bi the natural powers conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged into our ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and the excrementes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralli caſt forth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, as other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes be: but the heauenlie things, at the bleſſed bodi of our lord &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt, broken for vs, &amp; his bloud ſhedde for vs, vpon the croſſe, which we receiue bi faith, with al the bleſſed frutes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, that Chriſt bi his deathe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, aſcencion, interceſſion and prieſthoode, hathe obtained for vs. This ſwetelie and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablie we meditate in our mindes, bi the working of the holy ghoſt, it is diſtribute into al our actions &amp; dedes, and we are wholi receiued into Chriſt, to be one bodie wyth him, as S. Paule ſaieth. Heb. ii. He that ſanctifieth, and thei whiche
<pb facs="tcp:15988:11"/> are ſanctified are al of one. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine S. Paule ſaith. The cuppe of thankeſgeuing which we bliſſe. is partaking of the bloud of Chriſt: and the bread whiche we brake, is partaking of the body of Chriſt. For we (though we be mani) yet ar one bread, &amp; one bodie, in aſmuch as we al ar partakers of one bread.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe ar good words, but our ſir Iohn wil denie all this, and we muſt do as our curate teacheth vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>what teacheth he you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>That he offereth vp Chriſt in his Maſſe, for our frendes ſoules.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Yea but take awai moni that ye like fooles giue him, and he wil ſing another ſong. In verye dede, Chriſt was offered for our ſinnes,<note place="margin">Heb. ix.x</note> but that was once for al, and then he offered him ſelf vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe as our Crede ſaith, &amp; after he had ſo (by that offering) ſatiſfied vnto God, neither neded he anye more to ſacrifice, nor we ani more ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, for vs. For by one oblation once offered, he hath made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect vnto God, al that are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Sir Iohn therefore is a falſe
<pb facs="tcp:15988:12"/> Antichriſt, and a diſceiteful iugler in this point, &amp; teacheth his owne dreame, and not gods worde. And (I pray you) what woorde of God hath ſir Iohn, to hang vp the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in the pixe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Mary ſir it is a goodly ſight in the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>But Nicholas, oure crede ſaith,<note place="margin">Mat. xvi. Lu. xxiiii Actes. i.</note> that Chriſt aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in to heauen, and ſitteth on the right hand of God the father almighti. And S. Peter ſaieth: The heauens muſte receiue him, vntyll the tyme that al thing be reſtored. And the angels ſaid, he ſhould come from heauen as he aſcended viſiblie, &amp; ſhalbe ſene. Sir Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore doth great wrong to hang vp breade in the Pixe, and to make the people beleue, that it is Chriſtes bodye or Chriſtes Sacrament either.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>why, is it not the holy Sacrament?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>water in the fount, is no Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, but when it is put to the vſe that Chriſt appointed it, then it is a Sacrament. So bread &amp; wine are no Sacramentes, vntil they be put to the vſe that Chriſt appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that is, to be eaten in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce
<pb facs="tcp:15988:12"/> of his body broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and of his bloud ſhed: then are they Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, and the worthy recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath the promiſes of Chriſt, but the vnworthie, receiueth hys condemnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bread is made a gaſe, a pagea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of a plai, borne about for a pompe, &amp; han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vp to be worſhipped, it is an horrible abuſe of Chriſtes Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For Chriſt neuer apointed a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ſuch worſhipping of his ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>why, may we not worſhip the holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Yes forſoth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we do worſhippe it with moſt high honour, when we vſe it as Chriſt commaunded it to be vſed, that is, to eate the bread, and to drinke the cup, in Chriſtes remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Nai, ſir Iohn teacheth vs to ſai a pater noſter to the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to find a light afore it &amp; ſuch like.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>Sir Iohn hath <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  </hi> out of his owne brain<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nole. Chriſt nor his Apoſtles, nor any of the auncient doctours, neuer taught any ſuche doctrine: But I pray you, what can ſir Iohn do more?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Manye goodlye
<pb facs="tcp:15988:13"/> thinges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>what I pray the?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>He ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make holy water, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bread, holy palme, holy aſhes, &amp; holy candels.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>wherfore is holy water good?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>To driue a war diuels &amp; troublous dreames, &amp; to waſh away venial ſins.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>what calleſt thou veniall ſynnes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Light ſinnes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as ſwearinge of cuſtome, by gods bodye, ſides, woundes &amp;c. telling of ribauldry tales, drincking dronken, and kyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of prety we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe be horrible ſinnes in the ſight of God,<note place="margin">Epheſ. v.</note> and S. Paule ſaith, for ſuch thinges ſake, the wrathe of God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the children of vnbe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lefe. what calleſt thou deadli ſin?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Loſing of Maſſe, Matins, &amp; Euenſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, breaking of imber daies vigils and lenten.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Ah Lord, how you worſhip God in vayne,<note place="margin">Math. xv Eſa. xxix</note> being afraide to breake mens tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. would to God men were but halfe ſo ready to keepe Gods commaundementes. But what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medye for thoſe deadlye ſynnes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>we muſt be ſhryuen to ſyt Iohn, &amp; he ſhal geue vs penaunce.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:15988:13"/>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>what is penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>That our goſtly father enioyneth vs: as to ſai. iii. pater noſters, in the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip of God and ſaint Iulian, to faſt ſaint Anthonies faſt, or to ſay euerye daye our Ladies pſalter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>And are thy ſyns then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuen the, when thou haſte done thy penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>why not? whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue made amendes for them. Can God haue any more then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>Ye are deceiued Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas eueri wai. For firſt ye think that ſynne, whych in ſome caſt is done, and that, which euer is hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible and great ſinne afore god, ye count it light, and ſmal. or no ſin. Againe, ye thincke your ſynnes to be put awaye, for your owne pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce doynge, and for the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyneſſe of your owne woorkes, whych is to to greate a blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nichol.</speaker>
               <p>why ſhoulde I not beleue, that I am abſolued, when Syr Iohn layeth hys hande vpon me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>what ſaith he, when he abſolueth thee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Many good woordes, I warrant you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:15988:14"/>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>I trow ſo, but what I praye the?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>By my troth I can not tel, but beleue wel and haue well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>But howe canſt thou beleue that thou vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſt not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>I beleue if I be ſhriuen. the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he bea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth al the charge, &amp; not I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Olyu.</speaker>
               <p>So maieſt thou be eaſly deceiued. But Nicholas,<note place="margin">Ioel. i. Eze. xviii</note> true penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce, is a tournyng with the hart vnto God, hating and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of the ſin afore paſſed,<note place="margin">ii. Cor. v. Ephe. iiii</note> tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting to haue forgiuenes by Ieſus Chriſt, and fully ſtudying to liue a newe lyfe, in tyme to come. Thys ſhould ſir Iohn preache to vs in Engliſhe, that our hartes maye be brooſed vnto repentaunce, by the law, condempning vs, and quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned again bi the gratious promiſe of the goſpel. I ſay it ſhoulde be don in Engliſh, that we mai hear it, and vnderſtande it, beleue it, and ſo be abſolued from our ſins. For they that repent and beleue, are abſolued bi Chriſt, but ſuch as do not, ſir Iohn mai abſolue them at his pleaſure, but Chriſt abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them not. Therefore a latin
<pb facs="tcp:15988:14"/> abſolution, to an Engliſh ſinner, is as good, as a ſhulder of mutten for a ſycke horſſe. And thynckeſt thou, that thou art able to make a mendes for thi ſinnes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>whi not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>wherfore died Chriſt then?<note place="margin">Gala. iii.</note> if we could make amendes with our good dedes. what neded we Chriſt then? Neded his bodi to haue bene broken for our ſinnes, if our dedes could haue made amen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des? Or neded his bloude to haue bene ſhedde, if holy water coulde haue waſhed awaye our ſynnes? Chriſtes death were in vaine, if we by our owne merites, might haue deſerued reconciliation &amp; pardon at the hande of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>And ſhal I not do good dedes, faſt and pray<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and humble my ſelfe before God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Yes Nicholas, if thou be hartely ſory, thou ſhalt weepe and lament thy wickednes, faſt &amp; and tame thy ſinful carcaſſe, pray and inſtantly aſke mercie of God thi father. But yet al theſe cannot make amendes to God, for thy wickedneſſe committed, for then neded thou not Chriſts death, nor
<pb facs="tcp:15988:15"/> bloudſhed to be betwene God &amp; the, but thou wilt not forſake that I truſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>No, god forbodde I ſhould.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>Then marke thys wel, al thy good dedes are dewty for the time preſent, not amendes for thy time paſt. For if thou had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt done no ſinne at all, art thou not bound to kepe gods commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes? I trow yes. But if thou offend againſt gods commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, then muſt thou repent, &amp; turne to god, and aſke pardon in Chriſtes name, and ſo obtain for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes by his deathe, who hath made amendes for the, and from that time forward, walke in gods commaundementes obedientlye. And if thou haue hurt or harmed thy neighbour, reaſon wold thou ſhuldeſt make him ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. Didſt thou neuer fal out with non of thi neighbours?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Yes by our ladi, ſomtime.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>And didſt thou no diſpleaſure to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thine anger?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>No by god, but as I came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hai making, with mi pitch forke, I dabbed a Cowe of hys in the flancke, that ſhe dyed of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:15988:15"/>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>And what penaunce didſt thou for that ſpiteful dede?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>I ſaid .v. Pater noſters, in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God and the .v. woundes, and gaue a peny to a poore man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>Here if thou hadſt hadde a good ghoſtlye father, he ſhoulde haue enioyned thee,<note place="margin">Math. v. Luk. xvii.</note> to aſke thy neyghbour forgiuenes. and gyue him as much monie, as he hadde loſſe, by thy cruell and naughtye dede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Aſke him forgyuenes quoth a? I had rather his eien had bene out.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>I beleue the, God will not forgiue thee, tyll thys be done, if thou mai by any reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meanes come to hym. But I pray thee tell me, when waſt thou ſhriuen laſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>In Lent, when waſt thou ſhryuen?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>I am ſhriuen euerye day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſhryuen euery day? to what preſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>To the highe prieſt God himſelfe.<note place="margin">Pſa. xxxi</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>How canſt thou come to god, to be ſhriue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to him? Thou toldeſt me, that I cannot ſe him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>I doo not ſee him by bodilye eyes, but beleuyng hym to be euerye where preſent.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15988:16"/>
               <p>I bow mi hart &amp; kne to him, know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledging the great ſinne and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie that is in me, and beſeching his merci &amp; forgiuenes, of that which is paſt, &amp; his holy defence againſt ſinne, in time to come. And if ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing I perceiue my neighbour to be offended with me, if I be in the faulte, I ſeeke attonement, &amp; make ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des: but if he be in faut, I am content to forgiue &amp; pardon him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>But thou doeſt no pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Olyu.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, my hole lyfe is a penaunce, namely to mortifi the fleſh, and to ſtriue againſt ſin, and to forſake mine owne wil, obedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entlye to labour, to do the wyll of God. But what was thy penaunce Nicholas, when thou waſt laſt ſhri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>By god ſore penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>what a good felowſhip.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>I may not bewrai confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Tel me, I warant the, it ſhal neuer come out for me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Mai I truſt the.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>On my honeſty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Sir Iohn e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ioyned me to faſt al the fridaies in Lent, and the .v. Ladie eyens, bread and water.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>That was ſore penaunce for thee, that
<pb facs="tcp:15988:16"/> loueſt good ale ſo wel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that I ſhould ſeke (barefete &amp; wolward) our Ladye of walſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, and our Ladi of Pitie of Da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>How canſt thou ſeke them? they were deſtroied by king Henry the eight, a kinge of moſt godlie memorye, and deſtroier of ſuche manifeſt idolatries.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>That is truth, but ſir Iohn would haue me to be a beginne? agayne, of thoſe holy pilgrimages. For he douteth not, but within a whyle, we ſhall haue them againe, or els other as holye as euer they were.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>what had doſt thou don that he gaue thee ſo ſore penaunce?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Horrible ſinnes, I cry God mercye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Olyuer.</speaker>
               <p>what.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nichol.</speaker>
               <p>It chaunced to be holye day vpon a Thurſday, and vpon Friday mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or I went to the plow, I was very hungry, and forgetting what day it was, I thought it had bene Munday, and ſo I eate a pece of a ſhoulder of mutten vnwares. But god knoweth I was ful ſory for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>O greuous ſynne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother time, it chaunced the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice
<pb facs="tcp:15988:17"/> to be left at mi houſe, and one of the fete of it, hang out at a litle hole, and ſo I chaunced to touche it with my bare hands.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>That was not ſo great offence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>No was? Out ſir Iohn would ſing no more with it, til it was new ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed. And he ſcraped mi fingers till the bloud folowed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer</speaker>
               <p>Is not a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> better then a ſhepe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>Yes that he is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>Then whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is holier, thy ſkin on thy han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that God created, or the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues that the Glouer hath tanned, and made of a ſhepes ſkin?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>I trow the ſkinne of my handes is holier.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oly.</speaker>
               <p>why maieſt thou then touch the chalice and the cloute that couereth it, with thy gloues on, but not bare handed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke it is, becauſe I handle with my bare handes many foule thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as my fraile, my dongfork, mi ſpade, &amp; ſo euery man the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of his occupacion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>Oh I crye ye mercie, ye are none of the cleane fingred gentlemen: But Nicholas beleue me, all men know not, what they haue hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:15988:17"/> many times the night before they maſſe. But how ſai you to S. Paul,<note place="margin">Act. xviii.xx.</note> that got his liuing with the labour of hys owne handes? and wrought with Priſcilla &amp; Aquila, ſowing tentes, and leather coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Might not he (trow ye) touche the chalice, becauſe he had handled ſuche poore inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes as belonged to that occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Sir Iohn is none A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>I beleue that, nor yet Apoſtolike prieſt. For if he were, he wold neuer make men to ſhote at a wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g marke, with ſuch blinde ſuperſtitiouſe doctrynes: touche not, taſt not, handle not:<note place="margin">Collo. ii.</note> whych al periſh with the vſing of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; are after the doctrines &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of men. Didſt thou promyſe to do thy pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>Nay I bought it out partely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>Then I ſee wel, ſir Iohn is a Marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. what gaueſt thou for it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nichol.</speaker>
               <p>Tenne grotes, and ſo he changed my pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gremage, into .x. Maſſes, v. of the v. woundes of our Lord .iii. of the purification of our Lady, one of the holy goſt, &amp; one of Requiem,
<pb facs="tcp:15988:18"/> for al Chriſten ſoules.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>A mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunt in deede, that ſelleth fyne flower,<note place="margin">Apo. xviii</note> and bodies and ſoules of men: But who ſong theſe Maſſes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Sir Iohn promiſed me, to ſing them him ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>wel, that was inough for x. grotes: but how dyddeſt thou wyth thy faſtynge, woulde he not faſt for thee alſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>No he might not (he ſaied) for ſinging of Maſſe. For he muſt put wine in his Chalice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>The hipocrites binde heauy burthens,<note place="margin">Mat. xxiii</note> and lay them on mens ſhoulders, but they wil not once moue them with their fingers. VVoulde he in no caſe releaſe the?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, at the laſt he changed my faſting, to other good workes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Olyuer.</speaker>
               <p>what good workes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Gilding of an image of S. Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, &amp; another of S. Leonard, &amp; bying of an holy water far of braſſe, with a braſen cenſer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>This coſt the a good deale of ſiluer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>I had rather haue ſpent al the ſiluer that I ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this month, then haue faſted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>That knewe ſir Iohn well i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. And tel me one thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g I pray
<pb facs="tcp:15988:18"/> the. what gaueſt thou weekely to the collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the pore, when it was vſed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>I gaue as neibours gaue, thei mai haue a meſſe of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage at my dore, &amp; ſuch other, but ſiluer hath ben very ſka<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>It is very ſka<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, when we ſhuld do gods commaundementes, but we haue inough, to do our owne imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And ſe the iuſt iudgementes of God: you that hinched &amp; pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to geue .ii. pence, or a penye a weeke, to the poore of your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, which in dede are the very i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of God, and Chriſte, nowe ſhal ye be plaged with gilding &amp; painting of images, of tre &amp; ſtone, and with a great deale of like tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie, which are expreſſedly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden in the ſecond commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of god. And wher as for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the pore &amp; nedy, you ſhuld haue had gods bleſſing, nowe for painting and gilding, ye ſhal haue gods curſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>But our ſir Iohn ſaith, images are leud me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s bokes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Had he ſaid leud bookes, he had ſaid truly. I prai ye what had men learned of images, a ſore the
<pb facs="tcp:15988:19"/> of the ſcripture came amongſt vs? Learned we any other thing, then that the prophet Hieremye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth vpon, to lye, &amp; to forget God, and to runne after ydols, as the old idolaters did? Hereof cam our famous idols, at Ipſwiche, at VValſingham, at Canturburye, at Hayles, at Dunſtable, and euerye where. For the Iewes had neuer mo idols. mo blinde ſuperſtitions, mo deteſtable whoore huntinges, then we had. And al this may we thanck our holi ipocrites, biſhops and ſhoren greaſed prieſtes, that ſet vs to ſchoole, vpon ſuch blind bookes. VVho coulde .xx. yeares agone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſaye the Lordes prayer in Engliſh? who could tell anye one article of his faith? who had once heard of any of the .x. commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements? who wiſt what Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme ment? who vnderſtoode any point of the holye baptiſme? As for the Lordes ſupper, no man euer knew, whither ther were ani ſuche thynges, or no. Yf we were ſycke of the peſtylence, we ran to Sainte Rooke, if of the Ague, to
<pb facs="tcp:15988:19"/> Saint Pernel, or maſter Iohn Sho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: if men were in priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thei prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſaint Leonarde: if the welch man wold haue a purſſe, he praied to Daruel Gatherne, if a wife wer weary of her huſband, ſhe of fred otes at Poules at Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to ſ. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumber. Thus haue we bene delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with their images, &amp; thus we will be deluded ſtill. And our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lempne doctours preach as ſauer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the maintenaunce of theſe i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatries, as thoughe there neuer had bene ani ſuch things. But Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas, beware of ſuch bookes, &amp; ſuch leude ſir Iohns, that ſet thee to ſchoole vpon them. And harke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes, which ſaith:<note place="margin">Exod. xx.</note> Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen image, nor ani ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of anye thing, that is in heauen aboue, or in earth beneth, or in waters vnder the earth, thou ſhalt not bowe thy ſelfe to them, nor worſhip them. I a ſure the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas, the image made by mans hand, &amp; ſet furth to be kneled, &amp; knocked vnto, to be ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced, licked, and kiſſed, or any otherwiſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped,
<pb facs="tcp:15988:20"/> is a curſed of god, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, &amp; he that made it. And as the holi pſalme ſaith:<note place="margin">Pſa. cxiii</note> Thei haue eies &amp; ſe not, eares &amp; heare not, noſes with out breath, or ſmelling, ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds with out feling, feete &amp; go not, like the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mot thei be, that made them, &amp; al that put their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence &amp; truſt in them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Our forefathers had them in great worſhip.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>It is full true, that is bred in the bone, wil not out of the fleſh. Our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers &amp; grandfathers, wer delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with hipocrites, &amp; ſhal we be ſo to? I told thee before that our forefathers that we ſhuld folow, ar Chriſt, his prophets &amp; apoſtles, not our grandſires, &amp; great grand<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſires. And ſure I am they worſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped none, nor gaue ani commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, that we ſhould worſhyp them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>They are goodly thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges &amp; become the church wel. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the churches loked more like old barnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>Nicholas ye ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke like your ſelf. I am ſori for your old blindnes, that think al things goodly, that ſhineth gay in your eyes. &amp; ye nothing regard what is accepted in the ſight of god. wold
<pb facs="tcp:15988:20"/> it pleaſe ye wel, if one ſhuld come into your houſe, &amp; paint the wals with cow do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, or with maſer ſcou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rings</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhuld paint him with a cracked crown if I could co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e by him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>Then as he ſhuld pleaſe you nothing, but rather caſt you in to a futi, no more do theſe image-makers pleaſe god, but prouoketh his anger. For god (in the writings of the prophetes) calleth images dong, filthe, abhomination: &amp; the worſhyppers of them, he calleth whooremongers, backeſlyders, ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>agates, &amp; breakers of his league &amp; couenant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>we do not wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip the thing we ſee, but god and his ſaintes that ar repreſented bi the images.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ol.</speaker>
               <p>No image ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t god, as the ſcriptur ſaith plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>li. And I thinke, the apoſtles, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, martirs &amp; virgi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s neuer knew ani ſuch po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe or vaniti, as the pup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pets in churches ſeteth forthwith vain gilding &amp; painting, nether re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quire thei ſuch honors, but wolde we ſhould honour the Lorde our god, of whoſe goodnes they recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued ſuch mercie, to be made ſain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes:
<pb facs="tcp:15988:21"/> And to honour them, is to folowe their faith, in beleui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g gods word, and their vertuouſe life in keping gods commaundementes: and not ſo vainely without gods word, to paint and gild their images, to ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del them, and ſence them, and ſo commit idolatrie. VVhat and thy ſeruaunt ſhould ſerue thee, as he liſt, &amp; not as thou apointedſt him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Then woulde I giue hym wages, as I thought he had deſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued. and not as he looked for.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>How ſhal thy ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t know, what thy minde is, for him to do?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>He muſt aſke me, and I wyll tell him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>So then we muſt aſke at gods word, and learne there to know his pleaſure: and according to the ſame we muſt doo. But in this gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement is: thou ſhalt make none, thou ſhalt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip none. Now, were he a good ſeruaunt, that wold worſhyp the wyth breakyng thy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Nay by my trothe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>No more worſhippeſt thou god, or his ſaintes, but committeſt groſſe idolatrie. God is a ſpirit, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:15988:21"/> thoſe that wil worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in ſpirit and truthe. That is, we worſhip not god, tyll we doo (from the botome of the hart) acknowledge his almightye power, and goodnes, &amp; truly fear him, and truely loue him, and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly ſerue him, with the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful obſeruation of his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes. So ſhal we nede no vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible image, to expreſſe vnto vs the inuiſible God. And as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning worſhipping of the ſaintes, it is far other then painting or gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of images, or finding of ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes before them, as I haue before told the.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>And me thinck it becommeth the churche wel, and is a goodly ſight, to ſe the ſweete images, well paynted wyth fayre lightes afore them, &amp; a very good ſmel to feele the perfumes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſir Iohn ſenceth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>This is thy thincking, but S. Paule aſked the Corinthians, how agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the temple of god and idols. And as for candels, they dyd well in churches, when the people met in the night, as the old Chriſtians
<pb facs="tcp:15988:22"/> were wont to do for feare of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, and we do yet on Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas daye, &amp; Eaſter day mornyng. But in faire day light, men neede them not, and the images can not ſe them. And yf perfumes were burnt to purifi the aire in the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che, it is tollerable: but to do it, to the ſaintes, which are in heauen, it is nedeles, and to do it to the y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of ti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, or ſtone, it is ſtarke fooliſhe franſie. In very deede in the olde Teſtament,<note place="margin">Ex. xxxvii</note> God made a golden candelſticke, with lampes burning vpon it, in the temple, and he ordained perfumes and odours to be brent vpon his aultar: but at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Heb. ix.</note> thoſe Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh ceremonies ceaſſed. For when Chriſt (the true lighte) was come, and had ſhedde furth the bryght beames of hys Goſpell, then the light of faith nouriſhed wyth the oyle of good workes,<note place="margin">Mat. xxv.</note> ſo ſhone in the church, that is, in the faithful congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſtes diſciples, that al the world might ſee theyr faith, mekenes, pacience, goodnes temperantie, ſobernes, conſtaunt
<pb facs="tcp:15988:22"/> confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt, charitable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauoure to all men, with all other their good workes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; glorifi their father whiche is in heauen. Thus the ſwete perfume &amp; odour of the knowledge of Chriſte, fylled the hole world, &amp; in eueri place, drew the people to run vnto him, that is their moſt true louer euen our lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>wel, ſay what ye liſt, it is good to haue ſuch thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges in the church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ol</speaker>
               <p>what calleſt thou the church?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>The church (ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) wher we hear our deuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. Maſſe, Matins &amp; Euenſong.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>The church is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  </hi> beleueth &amp; profeſſeth the name &amp; doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt. &amp; right<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly &amp; deuli adminiſteth &amp; vſeth the ſacraments, as Chriſt ordained &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. And ſo we ar the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che &amp; temple of god<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; euery one of vs is a temple.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Are we the temple of god?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>Saint Paul ſaieth ſo:<note place="margin">ii. Cor. vi.</note> ye are the temple of the lyuyng God, as ſaith God. I will dwell amongſt them, and walke amongſt them, and wyll be their God, and they ſhalbe my people.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:15988:23"/>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>And is not our pariſh church an holy place, and the temple of god?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, if it be holily vſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>what calleſt thou holily v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>when gods woorde is preached, and the people taught to know one euer liuing god,<note place="margin">Hier. vii. Math. xx.</note> and his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, whom he hath ſent. But if gods woorde be blaſphemed, and railed vpon, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, ſuperſtitions, and idolatries maintained, then will God refuſe our churches, chappels, and al our aſſembles, and tell vs, as he tolde them at Hieruſalem, that we haue made his houſe a den of theeues. And in the reuelation of S. Iohn, thoſe places that refuſe Chriſtes word and goſpel,<note place="margin">Ap. xviii.</note> and maintayne falſe doctrine and idolatryes, are called Sodome, and Egipt, &amp; Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon, mother of whoredomes, &amp; abhominations, the dwellyng of deuels, and habitation of al foule ſpirites, and a cage of al vncleane and hatefull birdes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>well Oliuer wel, I feare me ye wil (one day) ſmoke for this geare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>whi Nicholas, what ſhould I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble
<pb facs="tcp:15988:23"/> with the, that art my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour? but plainly to tell thee the truth. what are our paryſh chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches now? Gods word is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wai &amp; caſt a ſide, as a thing of nou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght, and our blinde guides, mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vp their latin Matins, Maſſe &amp; Euenſong, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iuring their holi wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſalt, and geuing their holi bread, but no word of god is read in the mother tong to the people, no calling men to repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and amendement of lyfe, no mencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is made of Chriſtes death nor paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but all theſe thinges that our moſt godly kinges, with great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, coſt and trauaile, and wyth the paineful ſtudi of the Clergie, reformed in many yeres, all this (I ſay) haue the popiſh biſhops and prieſtes caſt downe, in one houre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, that am I glad of. For now I may haue leiſure to praye, afore we could not pray for hark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the prieſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>And didſt thou herken to the prieſt in dede?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Yea that I did.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Howe began he Matins?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>what wot I now?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>A goodly herkener,
<pb facs="tcp:15988:24"/> that toke hede to no worde that he ſpake. For haddeſt thou taken hede, thou moughteſt haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned many goodly praies. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he began Matins, ſaying: O Lord open thou my lips,<note place="margin">Pſalm. l.</note> and my mouth ſhal ſhewe foorthe thy praiſe. Yf thou haddeſt learned this well, &amp; hartely praied it, euerye morning, then ſhould not thy mouth haue bene thus ready to railing, ribaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie talke and ſweari<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, as it is. For doubtles God openeth not ſuche lips but the diuell openeth them. Neither is ſuch talke, gods praiſe, but his moſt hieſt diſpraiſe. Again what praier can be more godlye, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the verſe folowing, to be ſaid at the beginning of al thi labours? O Lord make ſpede to ſaue me. O Lord make haſt to helpe me.<note place="margin">Pſa. lxix.</note> And in the ende of thy day worcke, to ſaye prayſing God: Glorye be to the father, and to the ſonne, and to the holye Ghoſte: As it was in the beginnynge, is nowe, and euer ſhall be worlde wythout ende, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Sure I am Nicholas, ye can haue no ſuche learning nowe to
<pb facs="tcp:15988:24"/> pray. I pray the what ſaieſt thou in the Matins time?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Mi bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>Canneſt thou ſaye the Lordes praier?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Nay nor our Ladies neither. I can ſay mi pater noſter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>what is pater noſter?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Mary Pater noſter, what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye make of it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>A good Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas,<note place="margin">Eſa. xxix Math. xv.</note> you honor god with your lips, but your hart is far from him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>By God ſit, and we thincke on god &amp; our Ladi, when we ſay our Pater noſter, &amp; pray for al our good frendes ſoules, as wel as ye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke ye do. But what aſke ye of god, when ye ſaye: Dimitte nobis debita noſtra &amp;c?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I pray to God to haue merci vp on al Chriſten ſoules: and to ſaue their lyues, that I ſare better for.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>That is wel done. But why haue you not learned the Lordes praier in engliſh al this while?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>Sir Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had me, kepe me to mi old Pater noſter (for he ſaid the newe wold not abide alway. And nowe I ſee he is a true man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>And art thou glad, that the Scripture is taken awai out of the churches?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:15988:25"/>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Yea by my trothe am I, for we had neuer mery worlde ſynce this geare bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, derth, lacke of monie, and much trouble eueri where.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>O bleſſed god, heare the blaſphemies of the wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked world. Thei refuſed thi word (O Lorde) and liued a deteſtable life, and when thou plageſt them, to cal them to repentaunce, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, they receiued not thy correction, but aſcribed all thoſe euils to thy woord. But Nicholas Nicholas, troweſt thou that God wil not now viſet al your ſinnes, and puniſh them with ſword, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, wilde beaſts and famine? Yes trulie wil he, &amp; that the more ſharpely, becauſe that to all your old abhominations, ye adde thys blaſphemie, and are lyke the we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Iewes, in the tyme of Hieremie the prophet: who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when the holye Prophet rebuked, for their worſhippi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of Diana an he then idole,<note place="margin">Hie. xliiii</note> which idol thei called the quene of heauen. They wyth many ſtubburne wordes, layed al the blame of their miſerable cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie,
<pb facs="tcp:15988:25"/> vpon the prophet of God, and vpon his preaching, and ſaid, as ye ſay nowe: They had neuer mery world, ſince Hieremie prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, but thei were puniſhed, and euen ſo ſhal ye be.<note place="margin">iii. Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xviii.</note> The lyke dyd wycked Achab, he layed all the blame of the plages that god had ſent, vpon Helyas the Prophet. But Helyas aunſwered hym: It is not I that trouble Iſrael, but it is thou (O Achab) and thy fathers houſe,<note place="margin">Oſee. iiii.viii.</note> that haue forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lord your God, and haue ſerued Baal. So Nicholas lay the fault, wher it is worthy to be layed, and doubt ye not,<note place="margin">Prou. i.</note> but the day is at hand (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ye repent) that as ye now caſt away God and his word, ſo wyl god caſt you away, and as he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to you, and ye would not hear him, ſo ſhal you cal to him,<note place="margin">Pro. xviii</note> and he will not heare you. And you that haue ſtopped your eares, that ye might not hear the law, God ſhal ſtop his eares fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, &amp; your prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers ſhalbe accurſſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Tuſh, care not for that, God was neuer better ſerued, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is now, Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins,
<pb facs="tcp:15988:26"/> euenſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, &amp; maſſe, goodli ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with pryckſong, &amp; organs &amp; we do all good thinges, as we were wont to do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, yea, ye ſerue him, as ye liſt, and not as he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth. For he commaundeth you to beleue in his ſonne, and to folow his holy word; but thys ye leaue vndone, &amp; then ye pipe hym a daunce, on the organes,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Ther is nothing pleaſeth the.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>what can pleaſe ani Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hart, when he ſeeth gods worde ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide and contemned? But Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherefore ſerueth holye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>To light vp in thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, and to bleſſe men, when they lye a dying.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>The true light for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that lie a dying, is to know the ſweete promiſes of Ieſus Chriſt, howe he dyed for our ſinnes, and purchaſed for vs reſurrection and life: that euery one that beleueth vpon him, ſhould not periſhe, but paſſe from deathe vnto lyfe. As Chriſte ſaith:<note place="margin">Iohn. xi.</note> I am the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and lyfe, he that beleueth in me, although he were dead, yet ſhall he liue, and whoſoeuer lyueth, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:15988:26"/> beleueth in me, he ſhal neuer dy.<note place="margin">Ioh. viii.</note> And againe Chriſt ſaith: Verelye, verelye, I ſaye vnto you, if a man kepe my ſayinges, he ſhall neuer ſe death.<note place="margin">Iohn. vi.</note> And againe in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of S. Iohn: Al that the father hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, ſhal come vnto me, &amp; him that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vnto me, I caſt not away. For I came downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen, not to do mine owne wil, but his wil that ſent me. And this is the fathers wil, whych hath ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me, that of of al which he hath ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen me, I ſhould loſe nothing, but ſhoulde rayſe them vppe agayne at the laſt daye. And thys is the wyll of hym that ſent me, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueri man, that ſeeth the ſonne and beleueth on him, haue euerlaſting lyfe: And I wyll rayſe them vppe at the laſt daye. Thys lyghte ſo comforted Dauid, that he ſayed:<note place="margin">Pſal. xxvi</note> The Lord is mi light &amp; my helth, whom ſhall I feare. And agayne: Yf I ſhoulde walke in the myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the ſhadowe of deathe,<note place="margin">Pſa. xxii.</note> I wyll not feare euell, for thou (O Lord) art wyth me. Thys lyghte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted old Simeo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he ſaid:
<pb facs="tcp:15988:27"/> Lord now letteſt thou thi ſeruant depart in peace,<note place="margin">Luke. ii.</note> accordyng to thy word. &amp;c. This holi candel ſhone ſo bright in S. Paules eies, that he ſaid:<note place="margin">Phill. ii.</note> I long to be diſſolued and to be with Chriſt. This is our defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce againſt the thunder claps of gods wrath, that falleth vpon ſinners. And wher this holy light of gods worde ſhineth,<note place="margin">Ioh. viii.</note> men walke not in darkeneſſe, but haue the light of life. But wher this is not, what can thy holy candel do, but light the into a wrong belefe, &amp; ſo lead the into the darke dongeon of hell? wherefore ſerueth holye palmes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>To make croſſes, to bear in our purſſes, and to ſet vp. vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our windowes and dores, that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel come not nigh vs, nor into our houſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>what if the deuil be in the houſe, or euer the croſſe be ſet vp?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Then let him flye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way on the diuels name.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>How ſhal he flye out, ſeing the doores and windowes be ſo croſſed, that he dare not come nie them? Shall he creepe into the benche hole, or fly out at the top of the chymney?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:15988:27"/>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>He maye if he liſt, for I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue he hath no power to comeny the holy croſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>what if a croſſe were ſet there, made of an haſell ſticke, or of an vnhalowed palme? wer it not ſo good as this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>No mary were it not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>why ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>For this made vpon Palme ſundai, in the paſſion time, of halowed palme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>Se the craftie diuel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and how the people are deluded with blinde guydes. The old church kept a memorye the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day before Eſter, how Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes glory was openly receiued &amp; acknowledged among the Iewes, when they met him with date tree bowes, and other faire bowes, and confeſſed that he was the ſonne of God, commen into the worlde to ſaue mankinde, and the goſpel declaring the ſame, was apointed to be read on that day. But nowe our blind leaders of the blind toke away the knowledge of this, with their latine proceſſioning, ſo that amonge .x. thouſande, ſcarce one knew what this ment. They haue their laudable dumme ceremonies.
<pb facs="tcp:15988:28"/> with le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ten croſſe, &amp; vptide croſſe, and theſe two muſt iuſtle, til Lent breake his necke. Then cakes muſt be caſt out of the ſteple, that al the boyes in the pariſh muſt lie ſcam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling together by the eares<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> tyl all the pariſh falleth a laughi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>By our Lady I haue laughed well at it ere this.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Yea Nicholas, I warant the, the deuil laugheth ful merily, that he coulde with ſuche preatye toies, mocke out Chriſtes goſpel. And then, where the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fathers, apointed the hiſtory of Chriſtes paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to be read, that it being wel knowen vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they might the more depelier weigh the cauſes of the ſame, and profit that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vnto mankind, this the deuil, &amp; his miniſters moc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked out with the latin tong, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che many times neither the prieſt nor people vnderſtode. But Lord what Apes play made thei of it in great Cathederal churches, &amp; Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baies?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>what did they there?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>One comes furth in his albe, and his long ſtole (for ſo they call their girde that they put aboute
<pb facs="tcp:15988:28"/> their neckes) thys muſt be leaſhe wiſe, as hunters weares their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. This ſolempne ſyre, played Chriſtes part, a gods name. Then another co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panye of ſingers, chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and al, ſong in prikſong, the Iewes part. And the deuil (the dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>con I ſhould haue ſaid) read the the middel text.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>what dyd the preſt at the alter al this while?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>He ſtoode mum, and played Iudas, that betrayed his Mayſter. And in the meane time, becauſe it was teadiouſe to be vnoccupyed, ſuche playne ſoules as thou art, made croſſes of palme, to ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your dorss, &amp; to beare in your pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to chace awai the diuel &amp; god beforen. Hath not our ſpiritualtie well ordred this matter (trow ye) to turne the reading &amp; preaching of Chriſtes paſſion into ſuch wel fauoured paſtymes? But tell me Nicholas, hathe not thy wyfe a croſſe of palme aboute her?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Yes in her purſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>And a go on felowshyppe tel me, thinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou not ſometyme, the deuil is in her tounge? Syghe not man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:15988:29"/>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>I wold ſhe heard you, you might fortune to finde him in her tong and fiſt both.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Then I ſe wel he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth not in her purſe, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe the holi palme croſſe is ther but if thou couldeſt intreate her, to beare a croſſe in her mouth, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he would not come there neither.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Saye you what you liſt, the holy croſſe is good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, I take god to recorde, no man liuing, more highly eſtemeth the ſigne and token that Chriſt dyed on, then I do: but the holier it is, the more impietye is it, that the preaching of Chriſtes deathe and paſſyon, that he ſuffered for vs, ſhuld be ſet aſide, and the people deluded, with ſuperſtitious opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. For ſuch ſuperſtitious croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges, rather bring the dyuell to houſe: then driue him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, and ſuch as ye are, maye ſay what ye liſt, for the people lyked this better, then your preachings, and Sir Iohn hath willed the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh to bie a new croſſe, that we might folow the good lord again a preceſſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>why, wil he not
<pb facs="tcp:15988:29"/> ſay the Engliſh Letanie, kneling in the bodi of the church, that the people mai ſay it with him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Tuſh, we care not for it, it is left of long ſince, it is to teadious, we wil folow the croſſe a preſſion, as our forefathers did.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>O folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, it is great piti to ſe one blind folow another, til both fal in the pyt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Sir Iohn tolde vs,<note place="margin">Math. xv.</note> that Chriſt ſaid: If any man wil be my diſciple, he muſt folow my croſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>I can ſit Iohn thanck, he is a cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning coblet. The text (Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las) is thys.<note place="margin">Mat. xvi. Mark. viii Luke. ix.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Chriſte declared vnto his diſciples, that he muſt go vnto Hieruſalem, and there ſuffer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinges, of the elders, &amp; of the high prieſtes, and Scribes, and be killed, and riſe againe the thyrde day. Here Peter (of a good carnal loue to his maſter) toke him aſide and rebuked him, ſaying: Maſter, fauour thy ſelfe, this ſhal not be. Then turned he about, and ſayed vnto Peter: Come after me Satan, thou offendeſt me: becauſe thou ſauoureſt not the thinges that are of God, but the things that are of
<pb facs="tcp:15988:30"/> men. Ieſus then ſaid to his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: If any man wil folow me, let him forſake himſelfe, and take vp his croſſe and folow me. For who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer wil ſaue his life, ſhall loſe it: But whoſoeuer ſhal looſe hys life, for my ſake and the Goſpels, the ſame ſhal ſaue it. Here ye ſee what it is to beare the croſſe, and to folow the croſſe, and mark wel the order of the text: Chriſt decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red that he muſt ſuffer at their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, which in veri dede, ſhould of deutie afore al other haue glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied him, &amp; his doctrine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>who wer thei?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>The biſhops, prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes &amp; lawyers, as now adaies, one biſhop being a crafti lawier, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth more myſchiefe againſt the truth, then a. M. beſide ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do. And yet the ſame. with fained wordes of hipocriſi wil make al the world beleue that he ſeketh gods glori, the reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth of the people: Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas did when he ſaid in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel,<note place="margin">Ihon. xi.</note> it is expedient that one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> die for the people, &amp; that the hole na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> periſh not. So ſai they it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient that this doctrine of the
<pb facs="tcp:15988:30"/> goſpell be deſtroyed, &amp; the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers burned ſo ſhal we agre with other realmes, &amp; haue the hyeſt &amp; greateſt in the world, on our ſide. But Caiphas was deceiued, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wai that he purpoſed to ſaue the people, he deſtroied them, and his wiked cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel fel on his own pate, as it wil do (without dout) vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our hipocrits, at the laſt. Now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth peter, &amp; as much as in him is, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleth Chriſt to fauour himſelfe. But then Chriſt preached this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:<note place="margin">To folow Chriſt.</note> that thoſe that wil be Chriſts diſciples, muſt folow him, that is: as Chriſt moſt earneſtli &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantli did the vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that his heauenly father apointed him, traueling fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> place to place, preachi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; teachi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the wil of god vnto the people cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling them to repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; amend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of life, &amp; ſo won ſoules vnto the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>li father, ſo muſt al Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes diſciples do theyr vocation with faith &amp; diligence. And wold to God oure byſhoppes, woulde well looke vpon thys texte: for it principallye toucheth them. And to take vp hys croſſe dailye, is to ſuffer with patience the miſerable
<pb facs="tcp:15988:31"/> afflictions and tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, neede, ſorowe, ſyckenes, pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, loſſe of goodes, catels, frends and al other that god laieth vpon vs. To take theſe things with qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et mindes, knowledging that thei are laid vpon vs for our ſins, to kil ſinne in vs, &amp; to mortifi our fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſtes and apetites, to raiſe and ſturre vp true repentaunce, &amp; har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie inuocation vpon god, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently and faithfully to waite for deliueraunce at gods hand. Thys is to take vp our croſſes and to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt, euen to denie our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and to loſe our liues for hys word and goſpels ſake. This is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother maner of peece of worke, then to carye palme croſſes in our purſſes, or to go a proceſſion after a tinne, or copper, or ſiluer croſſe. This S. Paul reioyſeth in,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i. cor. iiii</note> ſaying: we alwaies beare about in our bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dies, the dying of the Lord Ieſus, that the life of Ieſu might alwaies appeare in our bodies. And again he ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">Gala. vi.</note> God forbid that I ſhuld reioyce, but in the croſſe of oure Lorde Ieſu Chriſte, whereby the
<pb facs="tcp:15988:31"/> world is cruſified vnto me, and I vnto the world, that is, the world greatli eſtemeth outward ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies and ſhewes of holines, as the Iewes mutch boaſted the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of the fleſh, and neglected the new creature of the mind, but Paul &amp; al true Chriſtians, reioyce not in ſutche outward ſhewes of holines, but in the true holynes of the hart and minde, and eſpetial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in this high benefit and gyft of god, that they ar called to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers with Chriſt, of the miſeries and troubles of this world. And as the world euer deſpiced Chriſte, and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted him accurſſed, and ſo put him to the moſt vile deathe of the croſſe: ſo hath it euer done by Paule, and al the Apoſtels, and all other that folow their doctryne. Theſe muſt be diſpiced and perſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuted of the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and not coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worthy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon breath<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; aier. And Paule &amp; his folowers the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſt, againe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne the worlde by the iuſt ſentence of gods worde, becauſe they refuſe Chriſt, caſt aſide the doctrine of
<pb facs="tcp:15988:32"/> his goſpel, and choſe rather to be leade in the darcke dreames, and miſtye imaginations of hipocrits, then in the cleare lyght of Gods holy ſcripture, and veritie, &amp; thus is Paule crucified vnto the world, &amp; the world is crucified vnto Paul God knowith, few bear the croſſe thus, and yet this is it that Chriſt requireth of vs, to be his diſciples to folowe hym, to denye our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and to beare our croſſes. This was not ſpoken of goyng aboute the churche yarde, wyth a croſſe borne vpon a ſtaffe, with a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly banner cloth, but to folow him in our vocation, leading a godlye life, and (as I ſaid) patiently ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring the tribulation of this world, for his woorde and truthes ſake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>Yet it is a good ſight, to ſe ſir Iohn, how he becommeth our beſt Cope, and vpon an hie daye to ſe al our Copes worne in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>why haue ye Copes yet?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, as ſaite as euer we had.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>were not ye ſworen to bring in al ſuch thyngs before the kings co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, but
<pb facs="tcp:15988:32"/> we brought in two or thre of the worſt, &amp; kept the beſt behinde ſtil.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Howe will you excuſe your ſelues of periury?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>we ar ſori that we brought in any at all, and as for periurie, let god &amp; vs deale it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>I am afraid it wil be a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable dealing, when god will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe to iudge the wickednes of ſo vnfaithful people, that nether fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth God, nor regarded the othe made by his name, nor yet the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of their king. It wer a much more better ſight, to ſe ſir Iohn become wel the pulpit, and declaring to the people, howe to folow Chriſt in godlines of liuing</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>what ſay ye to proceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in gang daies, when ſir Iohn ſaith a goſpel to our corne feldes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay nothing but this: ye that haue forſaken to folow god as he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth, ſhal be left to your ſelf to folow your own inuencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. And as for your latine goſpels, tead to the corne, I am ſure the corne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth as much as you, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore hath as much profit bi them, as ye haue, that is to ſai, none at al
<pb facs="tcp:15988:33"/> And manye times thys hath bene ſene, that the Clerke hath left the croſſe behinde him, and the prieſt his goſpel booke, and ſcant found the righte waye home, they haue bene ſo combred with malt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, &amp; miſeled with the ſpirite of the butterie. Trow you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god was not wel pleaſed wyth thys good Nicholas.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>I trow ſo. But fare wel, Maſſe wil be don, or I come.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>It makes no matter for one day. I wil read the a peece of the ſcripture in ſteede of thy Maſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>I care not for the ſcripture, and ſir Iohn bad me beware of it, for it wold make me an heritique.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>Sir Iohn then readeth not the Scripture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ncho.</speaker>
               <p>No, he ſaith he wil meddle no further then his portas.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>The Scripture is gods word,<note place="margin">ii, Pete. i.</note> opened to vs from heauen by the holy prophetes, Apoſtles, and Chriſt him ſelfe,<note place="margin">Pſal. cxix</note> it is the light to our feete. &amp; candel to our foote ſteppes:<note place="margin">Pſal. xix.</note> it is the law of life, vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed and holy, conuerting ſoules, it teacheth al things,<note place="margin">ii. Tim. iii</note> that is good perfect, rightwiſe &amp; holy, to make
<pb facs="tcp:15988:33"/> the man of God perfect vnto all good woorkes.<note place="margin">Pſalm. i.</note> He is bleſſed that ſtudieth in it day and night: but ſir Iohns owliſh eies, can not abide it. And as for his portas, ther is in it a meany of lies, craftili cloined, to deceiue ſuch vnſtable ſoules as delight in blindnes, deceiued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, and deceiuing other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>By our Ladye, ſir Iohn is a good prieſt, ſay what ye liſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Is ſir Iohn maried?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Nay,<note place="margin">Mariage.</note> he crieth phie on that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>what was the mater that ſir Iohn was afore the Shriefe of the ſhire, a while a go?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>A naughty queane ſlandred him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>wherwith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>She had a childe in an old baren, &amp; lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to the prieſts charge, that he begot it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliuer.</speaker>
               <p>Thinckeſt thou it was not a ſlaunder of truth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>Tuſhe, if it were hys, it was but a courſe of kinde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Had it not ben better ſir Iohn had dad a wife of his owne, as S. Paule ſaieth, to auoide fornication, let euery man haue a wife of his own,<note place="margin">ii. cor. vii.</note> and euery woman her owne huſband.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>what ſhould prieſtes do with wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues?
<pb facs="tcp:15988:34"/> Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faſt and pray, as their<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore fathers did, &amp; liue chaſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>Chaſt as ſir Iohn doth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>Tuſh he was ſhriuen or he went to mas, it was wel inough.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ol.</speaker>
               <p>Nicholas, I could ſai ſomwhat, of the vnwed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded prieſts chaſtiti, &amp; tel the many preti hiſtories how holili the fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es abſtaine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſnatching of goſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleſh, as oft as thei mai come to it But as S. Paule ſaith,<note place="margin">Epheſi. v.</note> it is ſhame to ſpeake thoſe thinges that thei do: &amp; for ſuch thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs ſake, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth the wrath of god, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vnbelefe, althoughe ye make a tuſhing at it,<note place="margin">i. Cor. vii.</note> &amp; deſpice the holye ſtate of wedlocke, in thoſe prieſts that be maried. Yet do their folow the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of God, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth that euery man haue his own wife, &amp; euery woman her own huſband, to the auoiding of whooredome. And agayne Gods worde ſayeth: If they can not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayne, let them marrye, for it is better to marrye, then to bourne. And againe Saint Paule ſaith: as concerning virgins,<note place="margin">i. Teſ. iiii.</note> I haue no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of the Lord. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. This is the wil of god, euen
<pb facs="tcp:15988:34"/> that you ſhuld be holy, &amp; that ye ſhould abſtaine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fornication,<note place="margin">Heb. xiii.</note> &amp; that euery one of you ſhuld know how to kepe his veſſel in holines &amp; honor, &amp; not in the luſt of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence, as do the Hethen which know not god. And again he ſaith wedlocke is to be had in honor, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the bed vndefiled, for whoore kepers &amp; aduouterers, god wil iudge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>This was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of men, but ſir Iohn is a prieſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>He is no angel, nor yet ſtock not ſtone, as apeareth by the preti babe. But Nicholas is not mariage an holi thing?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
               <p>Yes that is it, &amp; preſts tel vs, it is one of the .vii. ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>And is not prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode holi alſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>God forbid els.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>How chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth that holi prieſthode &amp; holy mariage ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not agre together no better.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>By mi truth ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I cannot tel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
               <p>I wil tel the. S. Paul ſaith: the ſprit ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth euidentlye,<note place="margin">i. Tim. iiii</note> that in the latter daies, ſome ſhal depart from the faithe, and ſhall geue heede vnto ſpirites of errour, &amp; dyueliſh doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryne, of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whych ſpeake falſe
<pb facs="tcp:15988:35"/> thorow hipocriſie, and haue their conſciences marcked with an hot yron, forbidding to mary, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding to abſtain from meates which god hath created to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued with geuing thanks, of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which beleue, &amp; know the truth. Here may al men, that wilfulli are not blynde, perceiue and ſee, from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce our preſts wiueles life, that condempne Matrimonie, &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſo hily their ſingle life, falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly named chaſtitie, commeth euen from ſpirites of erroure, from the deuil him ſelf, who with that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſnare, hath drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mani a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of ſoules, into moſt beaſtlye and filthie liuing. And this the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites know well inoughe. For their owne conſcience, is a witnes againſte them, that they liue not al chaſt, but yet though thei know the truth, of a ſet maliſe and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinatie, and for filthie lucres ſake they teach and maintaine ſuch a deteſtable eſtate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo as theues are brent in the hand with an hot iro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnto their ppetual ſhame, ſo theſe men are dailie burnt in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb facs="tcp:15988:35"/> witneſſing againſte them, that their doctryne and vnchaſte liuing, pleaſeth not God. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Nicholas, take hede of them, &amp; remember the old ſaying: prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes &amp; doues makes foule houſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nich.</speaker>
               <p>I warrant you for ſir Iohn, he is as honeſt a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (for an vnma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried prieſt) and is vengeaunce ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as any is with in this .xx. myle: and as good a companion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliue.</speaker>
               <p>what call ye an honeſt man, and a good companion?<note place="margin">A good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>A good fellow that wil kepe company all day at the good ale, anſt playe his xl. pence at diſe, with anye good felow that commeth: Yea, I haue knowen him kepe companye two daies &amp; two nightes with good fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowes ere this. Bi god I dare ſay this for ſir Iohn. if he wer as wel ſene in the chapters of the Bible, as he is in the tables, diſe and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, by God Oliuer, he might rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with the beſt of them, and yet I ſpeake not this becauſe I wold praiſe him. Yea, yea, I tel ye, as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle learning as he hath, he is a mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ren felowe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>Happye are the
<pb facs="tcp:15988:36"/> ſhepe that haue ſuch a ſhepherd, and the ſoules that ſir Iohn ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth for. Your Alewiues loue him wel, I dare ſay, and make much of him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nicho.</speaker>
               <p>By Saint Iulian, elles wer thei to blame, for he is a good cuſtomer of theirs, and ſpendeth more ſiluer among them, then ani ſixe in our pariſh, I dare wel ſay. The bel toleth, I haue loſt ſacrtng a vengeaunce on it, with babling with the. But yet I truſt to ſee my maker daunce about the cuppe: I wil runne a pace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
               <p>I haue loſt al my labour, with talkyng wyth him. Alas it is pitie to ſe the plain and ſimple people, thus deluded and brought to ſuche a miſerable caſe, that they embrace lyes, in ſtede of truth, and errour and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, in place of true godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and Chriſtian religion. But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen this was before prophecyed: that Antichriſt,<note place="margin">ii. Teſ. v.</note> the ſon of perdici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould come by the woorking of Sathan. with al lying powers, ſignes and wonders<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; in al diſcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueablenes of vnryghtuouſnes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that periſhe, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:15988:36"/> they receiued not the loue of the truthe, that they might be ſaued. And therfore god ſhal ſend them ſtrong illuſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that thei ſhuld be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue lies, that al they might be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which beleue not the truth, but had pleaſure in vnryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. But our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte will come ſhortely, and with the breath of his mouth deſtroye that aduerſary. He ſhal not be deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed bi ſwerd,<note place="margin">zach. iiii. Apo. xix.</note> nor ſtrength of mans power: but by the power of god, &amp; bi the ſwerd of his word. Come Lord Ieſus, lighten the eies of the blinde, conuert the hartes of thy people: heale our backeſlidinges, and treade downe Satan and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt his chaplaines. And let thi holye name and woorde, euer more and more, be mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified among vs, Let al true Chriſten hartes ſay A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:15988:37"/>
            <head>A DIALOGVE OR COMMV<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nication for two children, or vnlet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tred folkes, profitable and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye to be learned.</head>
            <p>WHo made you?</p>
            <p>God almightie.</p>
            <p>wherof made he you?</p>
            <p>Of the mould of the erth</p>
            <p>VVhat hathe he done more for you?</p>
            <p>Geuen his ſonne for me.</p>
            <p>VVhat is his ſonnes name?</p>
            <p>Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>VVhat is Ieſus?</p>
            <p>A Sauiour.</p>
            <p>How hath he ſaued thee?</p>
            <p>He hath redemed me.</p>
            <p>wherfro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath he redemed the?</p>
            <p>From ſinne, death &amp; dampnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>VVherewith redemed he thee?</p>
            <p>VVith his precious bloud.</p>
            <p>VVhat is Chriſt to ſay?</p>
            <p>An anoynted.</p>
            <p>VVho anoynted him?</p>
            <p>God the Father.</p>
            <p>VVherwith anoynted he hym?</p>
            <p>VVith the holy ghoſt.</p>
            <p>why is he called Chriſt, or anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?</p>
            <p>For he is king, hiſhop &amp; prophet.</p>
            <p>Of whom is he Kyng?</p>
            <p>Of al Gods elect.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15988:37"/>
            <p>VVhat doth he for them?</p>
            <p>Gouerne and defend them.</p>
            <p>VVhat is Chriſt more?</p>
            <p>Our highe prieſt and Byſhoppe.</p>
            <p>Howe is he prieſt and Byſhop?</p>
            <p>Ordained of God.</p>
            <p>After what order?</p>
            <p>After the order of Melchizedech.</p>
            <p>VVhat ſacrifice offred he?</p>
            <p>His own body vpon the croſſe.</p>
            <p>what doth he ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctifi bi <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> offri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g?</p>
            <p>Our conſciences fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dead workes,</p>
            <p>VVhat are dead workes?</p>
            <p>Synne and wickednes.</p>
            <p>VVhat is Chriſt els?</p>
            <p>The great prophet promyſed.</p>
            <p>VVhat is a Prophetes offyce?</p>
            <p>To declare the councell of God.</p>
            <p>what cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel hath Chriſt decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red?</p>
            <p>The goſpel of Peace.</p>
            <p>what is the Goſpell?</p>
            <p>A preaching of glad tydynges.</p>
            <p>what glad tidynges?</p>
            <p>Forgyuenes of ſynnes freelye.</p>
            <p>what calleſt thou freelye?</p>
            <p>It coſt them nothing.</p>
            <p>whom coſt it then?</p>
            <p>Our Lord Chriſt.</p>
            <p>what coſt it him?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15988:38"/>
            <p>His bleſſed hart bloud.</p>
            <p>To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is forgiuenes preached</p>
            <p>To al that repent and beleue.</p>
            <p>what muſt they repent?</p>
            <p>Theyr former euyl lyuyng.</p>
            <p>How muſt they repent?</p>
            <p>From the botom of their heartes.</p>
            <p>Muſt we not confeſſe our ſyns?</p>
            <p>Yes verely.</p>
            <p>To whom muſt we confeſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
            <p>To God, whom we haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded.</p>
            <p>Muſt we not confeſſe to a prieſt?</p>
            <p>Yes, when nede is.</p>
            <p>when is it neede?</p>
            <p>when we can not otherwyſe qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et our conſciences.</p>
            <p>wherfore ſhould we go to the prieſt?</p>
            <p>That he may do his office.</p>
            <p>what is his office?</p>
            <p>To preach the law and the goſpel and to abſolue vs.</p>
            <p>why muſt he preache the lawe?</p>
            <p>To brooſe oure heartes vnto true repentaunce.</p>
            <p>whi muſt he preach the goſpel?</p>
            <p>To teache vs to flye to Chriſte to rayſe vs.</p>
            <p>How doth the lawe brooſe our harts?</p>
            <p>It ſheweth vs gods wrath &amp; da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation for our ſinnes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15988:38"/>
            <p>How doth the goſpell rayſe vs?</p>
            <p>It ſheweth our ſacrifice and atonement maker.</p>
            <p>Who is that?</p>
            <p>The la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be of god, offred for our ſins</p>
            <p>who is that lambe offred?</p>
            <p>Ieſus Criſt crucified.</p>
            <p>How often was he offred?</p>
            <p>Once for al vpon the croſſe.</p>
            <p>who offred hym?</p>
            <p>Himſelfe and none other.</p>
            <p>Doth not the priſt daili offer him?</p>
            <p>No, he dieth no more, nor is no more offred.</p>
            <p>Is not the miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lords ſupper, a ſacrifice?</p>
            <p>It is a memory of Chriſtes ſacrifice,</p>
            <p>done on the croſſe for vs?</p>
            <p>Can we make no ſacrifices to god?</p>
            <p>Yes, iii. maner of ſacrifices.</p>
            <p>what is the firſt?</p>
            <p>Praiſe and thankeſgeuing, &amp; prayer to god.</p>
            <p>How is that called in ſcripture?</p>
            <p>The fruit of their lips, that confeſſe the Lordes name.</p>
            <p>what is the ſecond ſacrifice?</p>
            <p>Almes dede, &amp; mercy to our neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
            <p>How is that called?</p>
            <p>A ſwete ſmel accepted and pleaſing to god.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15988:39"/>
            <p>what is the third, ſacrifice?</p>
            <p>Mortifiyng of our carnal luſtes and deſires.</p>
            <p>what is that named in gods word</p>
            <p>A liuely acceptable offring to god?</p>
            <p>Can the preiſt abſolue vs from our ſinnes?</p>
            <p>Ye, if he repent &amp; beleue the goſpel</p>
            <p>what if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t not nor beleue?</p>
            <p>Then the priſt cannot abſolue him.</p>
            <p>what if he repent and beleue?</p>
            <p>Then the priſt cannot bynd him.</p>
            <p>Howe doth the preiſt bynde and abſolue?</p>
            <p>By the preaching of Gods worde.</p>
            <p>what if the priſt be ignoraunt of gods word?</p>
            <p>Then is he a blind guide.</p>
            <p>Cannot an ignoraunt priſt lead vs?</p>
            <p>Yes, into the pitte of hell.</p>
            <p>what muſt he do that is forgeuen his ſinne?</p>
            <p>Bringe fourth worthi fruites of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce.</p>
            <p>what ar worthy fruits of repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</p>
            <p>A godly lyfe amending that he before offended in.</p>
            <p>Geue an example.</p>
            <p>The dronkarde muſt leaue his
<pb facs="tcp:15988:39"/> dronkennes.</p>
            <p>Another.</p>
            <p>The lechourer muſt forſake hordo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </p>
            <p>A thirde example.</p>
            <p>The ſwearer muſt leaue ſwearing and honour the holy name of god.</p>
            <p>where learneſt thou this?</p>
            <p>In S. Peters epiſtle the .iii. chapter.</p>
            <p>what ſaith he?</p>
            <p>Turne from euyll and do good.</p>
            <p>what reward ſhal thei haue that do ſo?</p>
            <p>The grace and fauour of God, and life euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>God graunt vs all to doe ſo, and euer to walke in his truth.</p>
            <p>Amen, and thankes to God forthe light of his holy word and goſpel.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
